<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Sorrovves lenitiue Written vpon occasion of the death of that hopefull and noble young gentleman, Iohn Lord Harrington, Barron of Exton, &amp;c. Who died the 27. of Febr. 1613. By Abraham Iackson.</title>
            <author>Jackson, Abraham, 1589-1646?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1614</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 28 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04153</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14296</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S121030</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99856221</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99856221</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21750</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04153)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21750)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1522:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Sorrovves lenitiue Written vpon occasion of the death of that hopefull and noble young gentleman, Iohn Lord Harrington, Barron of Exton, &amp;c. Who died the 27. of Febr. 1613. By Abraham Iackson.</title>
                  <author>Jackson, Abraham, 1589-1646?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[40] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Roger Iackson, and are to be solde at his shop neere the great Conduit in Fleet-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1614.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B C⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Harington of Exton, John Harington, --  Baron, 1592-1614 --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21750:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21750:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>SORROVVES <hi>LENITIVE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written</hi> Vpon occaſion of the Death of that hopefull and Noble young Gentleman, <hi>John</hi> Lord <hi>Harrington, Barron</hi> of <hi>Exton,</hi> &amp;c. Who died the 27. of <hi>Febr.</hi> 1613.</p>
            <p>By ABRAHAM IACKSON.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>OVID. 4. de Ponto.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <l>Temporis officium ſolatia dicere certieſt,</l>
               <l>Dum dolor in curſu, dum petit aeger opem.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Roger Iackſon,</hi> and are to be ſolde at his Shop neere the great Conduit in Fleet-ſtreete. 1614.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:21750:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21750:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE AND VERTVOVS LADIES, THE Lady LVCY, Counteſſe of <hi>Bedford,</hi> and the Lady ANNE HAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RINGTON, &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Ho<hi rend="sup">nourable</hi>:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Our fauourable acceptance of my poore endeauours, in an Office of the like nature, hath animated mee againe to put Pen to paper, with a purpoſe to lenifie that bitter pill of Paſsion (which naturall affection hath once more cauſed you to ſwallow) with the ſweet iulip of Conſolation. And for as much as Phiſitians cannot well apply their Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dialls
<pb facs="tcp:21750:3"/>to the ſicke, till they know the ſyntomes of the diſeaſe; I haue (in a feeling ſympathie of your griefe) aymed at your Complaints, and haue written them according to my conceipt, not doubting, but (if I had beene Secretarie to you afflicted thoughts) I ſhould haue made them appeare more like themſelues.</p>
            <p>Next (as method in that caſe required) I haue ſet downe ſuch meditations of Comfort, as I thought beſt ſuting to your viſitation<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Beſeech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you to vouchſafe them as gracious a cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, as an humble and deuoted heart may be thought worthy to be allowed, that reſts, and euer will remaine</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours, ready in all humility to doe you ſeruice, ABRAHAM IACKSON.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:21750:3"/>
            <head>SORROVVES <hi>LENITIVE.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>When awleſſe <hi>Death,</hi> with poyſon-pointed dart</l>
               <l>Had pierc't Fames fauourite, yong <hi>Harrington,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That plant of Honour, through his gen'rous hart;</l>
               <l>Two mournfull Ladies, in affection one,</l>
               <l>(His wofull Mother, and his Siſter deere)</l>
               <l>From troubled thoughts, ſhed torrents chriſtall cleere.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:21750:4"/>
            <lg>
               <l>And as a day-long-labouring Husband-man,</l>
               <l>That with heart-fatting ioy doth feaſt his eyes,</l>
               <l>To ſee his full-ear'd Corne (with <hi>Zephyr's</hi> Fanne)</l>
               <l>Blowne on to ripeneſſe; if a ſtorme ariſe,</l>
               <l>That with ſterne blaſts deſtroyes the forward graine,</l>
               <l>Sits downe and wailes the loſſe of his long paine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Or as a Merchant, ſtanding on the ſhore,</l>
               <l>His long abſented Ship doth new behold,</l>
               <l>Entring the Hauens mouth, full fraught with ſtore</l>
               <l>Of Orient pearle, and pureſt <hi>Indian</hi> gold;</l>
               <l>If in his ſight the veſſell ſuffer wracke,</l>
               <l>Straines out with cryes, till heart with ſorrow cracke.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:21750:4"/>
            <lg>
               <l>So did the wofull Lady <hi>Harrington;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>When ſhe was reft of him, that was her ioy,</l>
               <l>Her loue, her life, her deere, and onely Sonne,</l>
               <l>Her eaſe in Mourning, comfort in annoy,</l>
               <l>Her greateſt ſolace in her moſt diſtreſſe,</l>
               <l>Her curing Cordiall in heauineſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So gracefull <hi>Lucy, Bedfords</hi> worthy Wife,</l>
               <l>When brute, too true, had to her eares related</l>
               <l>The ſodaine wracke of that beloued life,</l>
               <l>Whom diſmall Fate vntimely ſo had dated,</l>
               <l>Did caſt her ſelfe into the armes of moane,</l>
               <l>And to her ſelfe rip'd vp her griefes alone.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:21750:5"/>
            <lg>
               <l>And if a Poet may be bold to write,</l>
               <l>How he conceiues ſuch paſſions were conceiu'd;</l>
               <l>Then thus the grieu'd Lady Mother might,</l>
               <l>(With ſighes) bewaile her hopefull ioy bereau'd.</l>
               <l>Theſe broken accents, (Eccho's of her groanes)</l>
               <l>Might be the mournfull method of her moanes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O thou my deareſt deare, and louing Childe;</l>
               <l>Beſt part of me, deriued from my wombe:</l>
               <l>The ſole <hi>Idea</hi> of thy Father milde,</l>
               <l>My ſtaffe of age to guide me to my Tombe!</l>
               <l>Art thou extinct? hath life forſaken thee?</l>
               <l>Haſt thou relinquiſh'd all the world and me?</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:21750:5"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Wert thou not young, in prime of flowring life?</l>
               <l>Were not thy paſſions ſway'd with temperance?</l>
               <l>Were not thy humors in perfection rife?</l>
               <l>Wert thou not pious in perſeuerance?</l>
               <l>How haps it then, that thou wert rap't in haſt,</l>
               <l>When but the world began thy worth to caſt?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O art thou gone, and am I left behinde?</l>
               <l>Shall neuer more mine eyes behold thee heere?</l>
               <l>Muſt griefe ore-flowe the meaſure of my minde,</l>
               <l>vvhil'ſt houres co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pleat the daies, or daies the yeere?</l>
               <l>What ſight can pleaſe without the ſight of thee,</l>
               <l>Whoſe life, was life, whoſe death is death to me?</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:21750:6"/>
            <lg>
               <l>O had I all forgone what ſo is mine,</l>
               <l>Within the compaſſe of this maſſie round;</l>
               <l>Except that part of me that is diuine,</l>
               <l>Wherein th' <hi>Idea</hi> of my God is found;</l>
               <l>So that I had ſweet Sonne enioyed thee,</l>
               <l>Who being parted, parts all ioy from mee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O cruell <hi>Parcae</hi> now I ſee tis ſo,</l>
               <l>Ye are call'd <hi>Parcae,</hi> not becauſe ye ſpare</l>
               <l>The liues of ſuch, as worſt we may forgoe:</l>
               <l>But on the contrary, ye <hi>Parcae</hi> are:</l>
               <l>Becauſe ye plucke the buds with partiall hand,</l>
               <l>And let the riper fruits vngathered ſtand.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:21750:6"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Tis ſaid that <hi>Niobe</hi> was turn'd to ſtone,</l>
               <l>For wailing too too much her childrens death.</l>
               <l>Be't ſo or no; I haue more cauſe to moane,</l>
               <l>Whil'ſt ſoule and body are conioyn'd with breath,</l>
               <l>For her griefe ended, with her ended ioy:</l>
               <l>But mine ſtill liues, to lengthen lifes annoy.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Auctolia</hi> hearing but a falſe report</l>
               <l>Of her <hi>Vliſſes</hi> death, that (with more Knights)</l>
               <l>Did to the ſiege of tow'r-built <hi>Troy</hi> reſort,</l>
               <l>To quell the pride of <hi>Greece</hi>-abuſing ſprights;</l>
               <l>Renounc'd all ioy, turn'd ſolace into moane:</l>
               <l>Becauſe ſhe did but thinke her Sonne was gone.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:21750:7"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Oh what ſhall I doe? how ſhall I containe</l>
               <l>My ſelfe in ſorrow, that too well doe know</l>
               <l>The loſſe of him; that was my eaſe in paine,</l>
               <l>My greateſt comfort, in griefes ouer-flowe?</l>
               <l>How ſhall I keepe from breaking to extreames,</l>
               <l>That haue my heart ſo fraught with ſorrowes theames?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Let <hi>Niobe</hi> ſay what ſhe can deuiſe</l>
               <l>To aggrauate her ſelfe-confounding moane,</l>
               <l>And let <hi>Auctolia</hi> hers apologize.</l>
               <l>Yet <hi>Niobe</hi> became a ſenceleſſe ſtone:</l>
               <l>And <hi>Auctole</hi> wayl'd a miſconceaued feare:</l>
               <l>But true effects of griefe my heart doth weare.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:21750:7"/>
            <lg>
               <l>As would appeare could I <hi>Dole's</hi> language ſpeake.</l>
               <l>But Sorrow tyes the tongues of grieued weights.</l>
               <l>So that they muſt in mid-diſcourſes breake,</l>
               <l>And keepe the worſt behind to vexe their ſprights.</l>
               <l>Sith this is Mourners caſe; then thus in briefe,</l>
               <l>I grieue becauſe I cannot tell my griefe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus might a Poet ſhadow what ſhe ſaid;</l>
               <l>Though what ſhe ſaid indeed her ſelfe beſt knowes:</l>
               <l>As ſaying moſt when ſhe was moſt diſmay'd,</l>
               <l>In priuate ſort commenting on her woes.</l>
               <l>Next then we may imagine, as before,</l>
               <l>The noble <hi>Counteſſe,</hi> how ſhe did deplore.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:21750:8"/>
            <lg>
               <l>And if you can conceiue <hi>Polixen's</hi> woe,</l>
               <l>When her deare brother <hi>Troilus</hi> was ſlaine,</l>
               <l>By force of fierce <hi>Achilles</hi> fatall blowe:</l>
               <l>Or how that royall PRINCES did complaine,</l>
               <l>For <hi>Brittains</hi> hope, renowned HENRIES death:</l>
               <l>So might you think did <hi>Bedford</hi> ſpend her breath.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For thus, me ſeemes, her thought-bewraying tong</l>
               <l>Vtters the paſſions of her griefe-ſeaz'd heart,</l>
               <l>That doe in heapes vpon each other throng</l>
               <l>As though they would her ſoule and body part.</l>
               <l>O deareſt brother, ſoule-vnited friend!</l>
               <l>What timeleſſe hap wrought thy vntimely end?</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:21750:8"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Time turnes the Heauens in a certaine courſe;</l>
               <l>The Starres doe keepe their conſtant motions:</l>
               <l>Order directs the rowling Oceans ſource:</l>
               <l>Sence-wanting creatures keepe their ſtations:</l>
               <l>Mans fickle ſtate giues onely cauſe of ſorrow,</l>
               <l>That knowes his eue, but doth not know his mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Had I a Sonne to loſe (as I haue none)</l>
               <l>I thinke his loſſe could not more grieue my hart;</l>
               <l>Then thus to be left brotherleſſe alone.</l>
               <l>Who hath like wound, &amp; doth not feele like ſmart?</l>
               <l>To looſe a Sonne, yet might I haue another:</l>
               <l>But hopeleſſe am I left of any Brother.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:21750:9"/>
            <lg>
               <l>For looke how th'Elm e and Vine doe ſympathize:</l>
               <l>Or Wood-bind with the Haw-thorne doth agree:</l>
               <l>Looke how the Ivy with the Oake doth riſe:</l>
               <l>Or how the Steele and Load-ſtone natur'd be:</l>
               <l>So did we loue, ſo were our hearts affected:</l>
               <l>What one did fancie, tother ſtill reſpected.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But Death, the Author of Confuſion,</l>
               <l>That doth vndoe Loues hardeſt tyed knot,</l>
               <l>Breaking the bonds of ſacred Vnion,</l>
               <l>Caſting on blooming Youth, old Ages lot,</l>
               <l>Came with his woolly feete, but iron fiſt,</l>
               <l>And drew this Impe of Honour to his liſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:21750:9"/>
            <lg>
               <l>O world! no world; but Deaths <hi>Meandry</hi> maze;</l>
               <l>O maze! no maze: but to-end-poſting life;</l>
               <l>O life! no life: but Bauen-kindled blaze;</l>
               <l>O blaze! no blaze: but end of humors ſtrife.</l>
               <l>O moment ſtrife, blaze-flaſhing, maze of death,</l>
               <l>Whoſe end tends to the end of humane breath.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Swift is the Shittle in the Weauers Loome;</l>
               <l>Haſty the rayn-bred torrents riſe and fall;</l>
               <l>Fading the May-day flower, the Summers bloome;</l>
               <l>Vncertaine the rebound of Tennice ball;</l>
               <l>Nay, name I all the moment Types I can,</l>
               <l>Yet none ſo fickle as the life of man.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:21750:10"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Deuide an howre in equall-ſpaced quarters;</l>
               <l>Each quarter in his Minutes; Minutes againe</l>
               <l>In Seconds: then let skilfull'ſt number parters</l>
               <l>Their Arithmeticall choiſe Maxims ſtraine</l>
               <l>To part thoſe Seconds, in their ſingle prime;</l>
               <l>And that's mans meaſure in the clock of Time.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>All this is character'd in him, who was,</l>
               <l>Who was (O fatall word!) the Character</l>
               <l>Of Knightly Honour, Courtiers looking-glaſſe,</l>
               <l>Map of perfection, Vertues regiſter:</l>
               <l>But now is gone; yet left this name behinde</l>
               <l>For me, to treaſure vp in grieued minde.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:21750:10"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Which I will doe, (with true deuotion)</l>
               <l>Whil'ſt my world-wearied ſoule liues in my fleſh,</l>
               <l>And in my mirth, the name of <hi>Harrington</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Shall make griefes briniſh fountaine ſpring a freſh,</l>
               <l>And if my teares doe ſtint, or tongue doe faile;</l>
               <l>Know <hi>Sorrow</hi> wants both teares, and tongue to waile.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>As I was writing this conceiued moane;</l>
               <l>Mine eyes did let fall drops into mine Inke,</l>
               <l>Moyſting againe its drineſſe: whereupon</l>
               <l>My ſympathizing Muſe gan thus to thinke.</l>
               <l>I muſt not leaue theſe Ladies in this plight:</l>
               <l>For Inke made liquid bids me more to write.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:21750:11"/>
            <lg>
               <l>And as an Art-inſtructed Surgeon,</l>
               <l>(That hath ſearch't all the corners of a wound)</l>
               <l>Doth not ſo leaue his Patient but vpon</l>
               <l>The gaſh, layes healing Salues to make him ſound:</l>
               <l>So muſt I now (that haue ſo launc't your griefe)</l>
               <l>Apply ſome <hi>Cataplaſme</hi> for reliefe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Your loſſe was great, great Ladies I confeſſe;</l>
               <l>And ſuch as paſſion cannot but condole.</l>
               <l>Nay, <hi>Piety</hi> her ſelfe could doe no leſſe:</l>
               <l>As is recorded in Gods ſacred roll.</l>
               <l>For the beleeuers Grandſire did bewaile</l>
               <l>His deareſt <hi>Sara,</hi> when her life did faile.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:21750:11"/>
            <lg>
               <l>So holy <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> that <hi>Bellerophon,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Wept when his aged Father <hi>Iacob</hi> died:</l>
               <l>So did the kingly <hi>Prophet</hi> for his Sonne;</l>
               <l>The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> for <hi>Moſes</hi> alſo cried,</l>
               <l>And that which moſt in mourning makes for vs</l>
               <l>Our bleſſed <hi>Sauiour</hi> wept for <hi>Lazarus.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But yet that heathen howling out of meaſure</l>
               <l>Suites not with thoſe, for who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhed his blood.</l>
               <l>For ſuch repining drawes on <hi>Gods</hi> diſpleaſure,</l>
               <l>Tis but a ſhadow of a ſeeming good.</l>
               <l>A Hell-hatched off-ſpring of blacke-mouth'd Deſpaire,</l>
               <l>That doth Gods image in the ſoule impaire.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:21750:12"/>
            <lg>
               <l>O Ladies therefore calme your Paſſion:</l>
               <l>Make not your Noble harts Griefes chaire of State.</l>
               <l>Let it be pious <hi>Comforts</hi> ſtation,</l>
               <l>Your heart-tormenting care to mitigate.</l>
               <l>For <hi>Comfort</hi> is the <hi>Cataplaſme</hi> alone,</l>
               <l>That cureth care, ſalues ſores, relieueth moane.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thinke but how <hi>Iacob</hi> (after wearineſſe)</l>
               <l>Was by the dreame-ſeene Angels ſolaced:</l>
               <l>Or how that <hi>Proto-martyr,</hi> in diſtreſſe,</l>
               <l>Was ioyed to ſee Heauens windowes opened.</l>
               <l>Such will your ſolace be, and ſuch your ioy,</l>
               <l>If you encline to <hi>Comfort</hi> in annoy.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:21750:12"/>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Comfort,</hi> the ſtay of ſadded Chriſtians ſoule,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Comfort,</hi> the health of griefe-decayed health,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Comfort,</hi> the power of Reaſon to controule</l>
               <l>Sterne paſſion, that would get the heart by ſtealth,</l>
               <l>Will be to you, ſoule, health, and powre, &amp; caſe,</l>
               <l>Your ſadneſſe, ſickneſſe, weakeneſſe to appeaſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And as the precious <hi>Opall</hi> doth containe</l>
               <l>The beaming brightneſſe of the <hi>Diamond,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The azure luſter of the <hi>Saphirs</hi> vaine,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Emerauld</hi> in verdure goes beyond:</l>
               <l>So <hi>Comfort</hi> doth th' effects of peace embrace,</l>
               <l>And yeelds the fruits of mercy and of grace.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:21750:13"/>
            <lg>
               <l>But this is but as twere an outward ſhale</l>
               <l>To th' taſt-enſweetning Kernell that's within,</l>
               <l>The touching of the foote of <hi>Iacobs</hi> ſcale,</l>
               <l>Before we clime by it the heauens to win,</l>
               <l>The gentle ſpreading of the healing Plaiſter.</l>
               <l>To make it when tis on to ſtick the faſter.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>We therefore muſt apply this ſoueraigne Balme,</l>
               <l>This heauen on earth, this hold from Deſperation,</l>
               <l>This ioy in life, this tempeſt-laying calme,</l>
               <l>This hope in Death, this ſtaffe of preſeruation,</l>
               <l>Home to your hearts, to make you feele againe</l>
               <l>The ioy you had, before you had this paine.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:21750:13"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Had you a Sonne? Had you a louing Brother?</l>
               <l>Had you a Comfort? You what you held deere?</l>
               <l>Had you no more? Nor had you any other?</l>
               <l>And is he reft away, to both ſo neere?</l>
               <l>Yet waigh but both your happineſſe in his;</l>
               <l>And tell me then if you be void of bliſſe?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He was your Sonne: but now he is a Saint.</l>
               <l>He was your Brother: now an Angels Mate.</l>
               <l>He was your Comfort: now no cauſe of plaint.</l>
               <l>He was your deere: but now in better ſtate.</l>
               <l>You had no more, make that your cauſe of woe,</l>
               <l>Becauſe you had no more, ſo to beſtowe.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:21750:14"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Tis true his body was of perfect mould,</l>
               <l>And ſuch as might haue giuen his ſoule content,</l>
               <l>For one whole age a Manſion there to hold,</l>
               <l>Where euery part did homage to her bent:</l>
               <l>Reaſon ſate Regent, and the will obayed,</l>
               <l>All Paſſions by theſe two, were mildely ſwayed.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Tis true, he was a modell of perfection,</l>
               <l>Furniſht with rareſt gifts of Natures ſtore,</l>
               <l>Endowed with ſanctity, the ſoules refection.</l>
               <l>Was what his yeeres could yeeld, and ſomewhat more.</l>
               <l>For in his prime of youthly iolity,</l>
               <l>He was repleat with graue morality.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:21750:14"/>
            <lg>
               <l>His auncient birth might be (as oft it is)</l>
               <l>The foſter-Nurſe of ſelfe-vp-puffing pride:</l>
               <l>But his faire thoughts ſoar'd higher farre then this,</l>
               <l>And ſuch vaine-glorious humours he defi'd.</l>
               <l>With thriftleſſe Prodigalls he did not ſort,</l>
               <l>True Bounties meaſure did his ſtate ſupport.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So that a man might thinke he had beene ſent</l>
               <l>As a choiſe Iewell from Gods treaſury,</l>
               <l>T'adorne the world, and not as though God meant</l>
               <l>To ſhew him vs, and forthwith preſently</l>
               <l>To take him from vs, in his deepe diſpleaſure,</l>
               <l>Seeing vs ſo vnworthy ſuch a treaſure.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:21750:15"/>
            <lg>
               <l>But Ladies, this is not your caſe alone.</l>
               <l>Twas <hi>Iuda's</hi> caſe, when their <hi>Ioſiah</hi> fell:</l>
               <l>Twas <hi>Englands</hi> caſe their <hi>Edward</hi> being gone.</l>
               <l>Twas <hi>Brittains</hi> caſe, when HENRY bid farewell.</l>
               <l>HENRY a Maſter-piece of Natures mould,</l>
               <l>The young mans hope, the refuge of the old.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>HENRY, that was your Sons, your Brothers Lord:</l>
               <l>HENRY, whom he in vertue imitated:</l>
               <l>HENRY, by whoſe example he was ſtor'd</l>
               <l>With noble-minded thoughts, to heauen elated:</l>
               <l>HENRY, that lou'd him, &amp; well knew his merit,</l>
               <l>His faith, his conſtancie, and noble ſpirit.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:21750:15"/>
            <lg>
               <l>HENRY, to whom his heart was ſo affected,</l>
               <l>That if he might haue ranſom'd him from Death,</l>
               <l>He would (with dreadleſſe loyall zeale directed)</l>
               <l>Haue ſpent his deereſt life-maintaining breath.</l>
               <l>But <hi>Adams</hi> heires, each one ingaged ſtand,</l>
               <l>To pay this forfeiture of Natures band.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Sith this is that which euery man can tell:</l>
               <l>As being compos'd of brickle walls of mud:</l>
               <l>And that your caſe doth want no paralell,</l>
               <l>As we haue inſtanc't in the Royall bloud;</l>
               <l>Then let this meditation ſtill your crye;</l>
               <l>That he that now is dead, was borne to dye.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:21750:16"/>
            <lg>
               <l>You begge of God (in daily Orizons)</l>
               <l>That his all-guiding will be done in earth,</l>
               <l>As well as in th'heauenly Manſions,</l>
               <l>Where bleſſed ſoules doe liue in dateleſſe mirth.</l>
               <l>Tis graunted what you aske, his will is done:</l>
               <l>For twas his will to take to him your Sonne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thinke how that Mother-virgin, holy, pure,</l>
               <l>That bleſſed <hi>Phoenix</hi> of all woman-hood,</l>
               <l>Did with faith-armed patience endure</l>
               <l>To ſee the ſpilling of her <hi>Sauiours</hi> blood;</l>
               <l>To ſee his precious ſide ſtreame blood &amp; water,</l>
               <l>That was her Sonne, her Brother, and Creator.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:21750:16"/>
            <lg>
               <l>That was that Lambe of God, in whom was found</l>
               <l>No ſpot of ſinne, whom no default could touch.</l>
               <l>This might with dole her humane heart confound:</l>
               <l>But that ſhe knew Gods prouidence was ſuch.</l>
               <l>Againſt the which we ought not to repine.</l>
               <l>True Chriſtian will bends to the will diuine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>How willingly did <hi>Abraham</hi> obey</l>
               <l>That dire commaund, when he was ready preſt</l>
               <l>With his owne hands his onely Sonne to ſtay?</l>
               <l>His Faith taught him that all was for the beſt</l>
               <l>That God appoints, though we cannot conceiue,</l>
               <l>The ſearchleſſe depth, from whence we good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:21750:17"/>
            <lg>
               <l>What was your Sonne? and doe but rightly ſcan;</l>
               <l>Was he more deere and precious vnto you</l>
               <l>Then <hi>Abra'ms</hi> Son, or elſe the SON OF MAN?</l>
               <l>Muſt you be priuiledg'd when Death is due</l>
               <l>By Gods award? Let not your faith be cold</l>
               <l>In him that can returne Sonnes thouſand fold.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The little Sparrow fall's not to the ground,</l>
               <l>Without Gods fore-decreeing prouidence;</l>
               <l>And ſhall we thinke that man (in whom is found</l>
               <l>The ſubſtance of the Creators quinteſſence)</l>
               <l>Can be depriu'd of life if he doe nill,</l>
               <l>Whoſe ſupreame powre drawes goodnes out of ill?</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:21750:17"/>
            <lg>
               <l>He left you and the world you ſay too ſoone.</l>
               <l>Paſſion ſaith this: nay, Reaſon ſaith ſo too.</l>
               <l>But how? with this fore-thought diſtinction,</l>
               <l>Not for himſelfe too ſoone, too ſoone for you.</l>
               <l>For you: becauſe your earthly ioy's bereauen.</l>
               <l>Not for himſelfe: who ioy enioyes in heauen.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What can you tell God hath for you ordain'd?</l>
               <l>Or to what end your dayes he hath deſign'd?</l>
               <l>Muſt his eterne decree be ſo reſtrain'd,</l>
               <l>As that it ſhould be fitted to your minde?</l>
               <l>Little know we what comfort may abound,</l>
               <l>vvhen with Deſpaire Sathan would vs confound.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:21750:18"/>
            <lg>
               <l>When was your Patience euer tri'd before</l>
               <l>By any vncouth wracke of humane chance?</l>
               <l>God hath you bleſt with Honours, wealth, &amp; ſtore,</l>
               <l>And on you many bleſſings did aduance.</l>
               <l>Becauſe your friends firſt die, is this a wrong?</l>
               <l>All ſorts ſee that, chiefe thoſe, whoſe liues are long.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Would you (as earth-bred mortalls all deſire,</l>
               <l>That ſolace in this vale of miſery)</l>
               <l>Wiſh that you might, to what you would aſpire</l>
               <l>And not beawed by the Deity!</l>
               <l>Then you depriue your ſelfe of that ſweet boaſt</l>
               <l>Whom God moſt loues, thoſe he doth chaſtice moſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:21750:18"/>
            <lg>
               <l>This fickle life is but a ſwift-runne race:</l>
               <l>A doubtfull-ending combat ſtrugling ſtill:</l>
               <l>Vpon the troubled Seas, a Sailers caſe:</l>
               <l>A Captiues lot, fetter'd againſt his will:</l>
               <l>A toyleſome labour, full of ſweating paine:</l>
               <l>A iourney peſtered with winde and raine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O happy he, that firſt doth gaine the price:</l>
               <l>Happy, that ſooneſt doth the conqueſt winne:</l>
               <l>Happy, that findes the Port ere ſtormes ariſe:</l>
               <l>Happy, quicke ſhaking off the chaines of ſinne:</l>
               <l>Happy, the lab'rour at the cloſe of day:</l>
               <l>Happy, the trauailer, that ends his way.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:21750:19"/>
            <lg>
               <l>If theſe be happy, happy then is he,</l>
               <l>That hath ſo ſoone runne out his irkſome race,</l>
               <l>Obtain'd the conqueſt, got the Port, is free,</l>
               <l>Ended his worke, come home in happy caſe;</l>
               <l>If he be happy: you are happy too,</l>
               <l>That he was yours, although not now with you.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>His life was ſeaſoned with the thoughts of Death.</l>
               <l>Witneſſe his ſanctimonious purity,</l>
               <l>Witneſſe his words ſpoke with his lateſt breath,</l>
               <l>To you his wofull Mother ſitting by.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lord</hi> LESV <hi>come, to thee my ſoule I giue,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thou dy'dſt for me, that I with thee might liue.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:21750:19"/>
            <lg>
               <l>To him therefore, that thus had fixt his minde,</l>
               <l>Death was the greateſt Comfort that could be,</l>
               <l>The inſtrumentall meanes that he could finde,</l>
               <l>Out of his bodies Goale to be ſet free:</l>
               <l>As being the key t'vnlocke the priſon dore,</l>
               <l>That was by youthfull ſtrength kept faſt before.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And as ſome Knight, edg'd with the thoughts of glory,</l>
               <l>Hauing with pow'rfull Enſignes conquered</l>
               <l>Some ſpatious, waſt vnfertile territory,</l>
               <l>Hath yet a fairer Land diſcouered:</l>
               <l>But knowes not how it's faire ſhoares to recouer,</l>
               <l>Vnleſſe he had ſome meanes to paſſe him ouer.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:21750:20"/>
            <lg>
               <l>So this young Lord, this worthy Chriſtian Knight,</l>
               <l>Armed according to Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> direction,</l>
               <l>Hauing ſubdu'd that damned ſubtill ſpright,</l>
               <l>And brought the world and fleſh to his ſubiection;</l>
               <l>He did, with <hi>Moſes,</hi> on mount <hi>Nebo</hi> ſtand,</l>
               <l>And ken'd the heauenly <hi>Canaans</hi> promis'd Land.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But knew not how that <hi>Eden</hi> Land to gaine,</l>
               <l>Vnleſſe Death gaue him waſtage to the ſhoare,</l>
               <l>VVilling to vndergoe what ſo euer paine,</l>
               <l>VVere it to hale the Ropes, or tugge the Oare.</l>
               <l>Death therefore graunted what he did deſire,</l>
               <l>Taking nought but his earthes part for her hire.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:21750:20"/>
            <lg>
               <l>VVhat ſhall I ſay? Death was to him no more,</l>
               <l>But a griefe-ending ſweet Cataſtrophe:</l>
               <l>A paſſage from this worlds <hi>Aegiptian</hi> ſhore:</l>
               <l>To <hi>Canaan</hi> aboue through the red Sea:</l>
               <l>A Sunne to melt his liues congealed Froſt:</l>
               <l>A landing of his Ship in tempeſt toſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>As was the glorious <hi>Angell</hi> that conuay'd</l>
               <l>The bleſſed <hi>Peter</hi> from the loathſome darke:</l>
               <l>As was mount <hi>Ararat,</hi> on whoſe top ſtay'd</l>
               <l>The righteous <hi>Noah's</hi> deluge-waſhed <hi>Arke:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Laſtly, Death was to him, but as a Page,</l>
               <l>That lights a Taper to an vpper Stage.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>All which in time it will be vnto vs,</l>
               <l>If we doe act our parts as he did his.</l>
               <l>For then, when Conſcience ſhall our deeds diſcuſſe,</l>
               <l>She will aſſure vs of eternall bliſſe.</l>
               <l>As him ſhe did, whoſe faith had apprehended,</l>
               <l>The ioyes of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, before earths date was ended.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:21750:21"/>
            <lg>
               <l>His ſoule brook't no delayes from heauens delight,</l>
               <l>Loathing to be ſinne-ſoyl'd with this groſſe ayre,</l>
               <l>But ſweetly offer'd vp his virgin ſpright</l>
               <l>To her great Maker, chaſt, and ſpotleſſe faire;</l>
               <l>Where he doth ioy: for whom we ſo do mourne,</l>
               <l>Wiſhing vs there, and not his owne returne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thrice bleſt immortall ſoule reſt then in bliſſe,</l>
               <l>Enioy thoſe ioyes, for which thou wer't prepard:</l>
               <l>VVe know our fault, and Loue leades vs amiſſe,</l>
               <l>To grudge that thou with Angels bliſſe haſt ſhar'd</l>
               <l>Not that we ought, but good to thee bequeaue;</l>
               <l>But grieu'd ſo ſoone, thy ſweet conſort to leaue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And you ſad Ladies that are clad in blacke,</l>
               <l>Beſt ſuting with thoſe weights, that Sorrow feeds,</l>
               <l>Think what this WORTHY hath, &amp; what you lack,</l>
               <l>And you wil find your owne-caſe wants ſuch weeds.</l>
               <l>For mortall you, in cares doe draw your breath,</l>
               <l>Immortall he, needes none to waile his death.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:21750:21"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
